Inventory of the Chasovoi records
Hoover Institution Archives
Chasovoi records
1898-1981
82067
Chasovoi.
Orekhov, Vasilii Vasil'evich, 1896-1990.
4 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box. (3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection relates to the publication of Chasovoi, a Russian émigré periodical published in Paris; Russian émigré affairs; Russian nationalism, monarchism and anti-communism; and events in the Soviet Union since World War I. It consists of correspondence, serial issues, clippings, brochures, histories, other writings, and photographs.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The Chasovoi was a prominent anti-Bolshevik White émigré military journal printed in France, later in Belgium. The records were collected by Vasilii Vasil'evich Orekhov, a Russian military and social activist, who was the editor of Chasovoi. The journal covered the activities of the Russkiĭ Obshche-Voinskiĭ Soiuz (ROVS), Rossiĭskoe Natsional'noe Ob"edinenie (RNO), and other Russian White émigré organizations.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Chasovoi file consists of writings submitted to the editorial board, publications, reader reviews, and materials relating to Chasovoi anniversaries. The V. V. Orekhov file contains correspondence related to publication and notes to his lectures on military strategy, as well as broadcast transcripts of the Russian section of the Portuguese radio in Lisbon, which was started by Orekhov. The Russian White émigré organizations file consists of correspondence, articles, leaflets, appeals, programs, and clippings reflecting activities of the most influential military émigré organizations. More materials relating to Russian White émigré life in France and Belgium may be found in Printed matter. The transliteration of Russian titles of documents preserves the author's pre-1918 style spelling.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series: Chasovoi file, V. V. Orekhov file, Russian White émigré organizations file, Printed matter, Photographs, and Maps.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Romanov, House of.; Anti-communist movements.; Nationalism--Russia.; Russian periodicals.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.; Soviet Union--History.
Collection Contents
- Chasovoi file, 1923-1981. (Box 1-2)
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Magazine illustration portfolio, undated (Folder 1: 1-2)
  - Memoirs, essays, and articles submitted to the editorial board, 1923-1978
  - "Iz vospominaniĭ leĭb" gvardii Preobrazhenskago polka polkovnika barona Sergeia Aleksandrovicha Tornau. Chast' III. Chetyre goda smuty," undated (Folder 1: 3)
  - "Kar'era Chubura. Povest' iz sovetskoĭ deĭstvitel"nosti," by Roman Iagotyn'skiĭ, undated (Folder 1: 4)
  - "Rossiia v" Velikoĭ voĭnne,", undated (Folder 1: 5)
  - "Velikiĭ Kniaz' Sergiĭ Michailovich" (1870-1918), General"-Inspektor" russkoĭ artillerii (1904-1918), ego shizn' i deiatel'nost'," by A. N. Vinogradskiĭ, 1923 (Folder 1: 6)
  - "Krasnaia Armiia. Pechataetsia po rasporiazheniiu generala Kutepova," typescript, 1929 (Folder 1: 7)
  - "Opisanie ubiĭstva polk. Vl. Mikh. Bykova i kap. Alek. Serg. Kolobova strelkami L. Gv. I-go strelkovago polka 1 Avgusta 1917 goda," Koval'kov. Includes "Primechaniia k" ubiĭstvy..," by V. Granberg", 1935 and "Obshchiĭ spisok g.g. ofitserov" L. Gv. I-go strelkovago Ego Velichestva polka ubitykh ili skonchavshikhsia ot ran vo vremia Velikoĭ voĭny 1914-1917 goda" (Folder 1: 8)
  - Articles, 1949-1953 and undated (Folder 1: 9)
  - "Russkiĭ legion chesti," by V. Vasl'ev, 1961 (Folder 1: 10)
  - "Viet Nam. Doklad 13 Maia 1967." (Folder 1: 11)
  - "Smerdiakovshchina. Iz zapiseĭ sovremennika," by Viktor Rostopchin, 1978 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Reader reviews on publications, 1929-1981. Includes a scrapbook (Folder 1: 13-14)
  - Reader reviews on publications, 1929-1981 (contd.) (Folder 2: 1-2)
  - Publications, 1930 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Financial statements for magazine printing services, 1954-1966 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Collaboration with Le Bulletin d'information, Belgium, circa 1960 (Folder 2: 5-6)
  - Chasovoĭ anniversaries, correspondence and printed matter, 1968-1979 (Folder 2: 7-12)
- V. V. Orekhov file, 1927-1980. (Box 2-3)
  Arranged in three groups by format, then chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1927-1980
    - General, 1927-1980 (Folder 2: 13-14)
    - Abramov, Fëdor Fëdorovich, 1935-1937 (Folder 2: 15)
    - Andreev, Nikolaĭ Efremovich, 1974 (Folder 2: 16)
    - Gartman, Boris Egorovich, 1928-1929 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Kopański, Stanislaw, 1972 (Folder 2: 18)
    - Kowerda, Boris, 1942-1945 (Folder 2: 19)
    - Krasnov, Pëtr Nikolaevich, 1932-1941 (Folder 3: 1-2)
    - Mannergeĭm, Gustav Karlovich, 1933-1941 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Molitor, A., 1968 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Niessel, Henry Albert, 1935 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Pirozhkova, Vera, 1968 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Shteĭfon, Boris Aleksandrovich, 1939-1941 (Folder 3: 7)
    - Solonevich, Ivan Luk'ianovich, 1936-1941 (Folder 3: 8)
    - Woyĭchekhowski, Georg L., 1932-1944 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Lectures on military strategy, Paris, 1930-1932. (Folder 3: 10-12)
    Notes, graphics, and clippings
  - "Fondation Convergence Occidentale," Russian radio broadcasts transcript and correspondence, Lisbon, Portugal, 1972-1974 (Folder 3: 13)
- Russian White émigré organizations file, 1914-1953. (Box 3-4)
  Contains correspondence, articles, leaflets, appeals, programs, and clippings arranged in alphabetical order by organization.
  - General, 1914-1941
    - Prikazy i Prikazaniia Verkhovnago Glavnokomanduiushchego, Nachal'nika Shtaba, Garnizonu g. Mogileva, Armii i Flotu, 1914-1917 (Folder 3: 14-21)
    - Appeals, reports, photographs, and printed matter, 1924-1941 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Komitet Ob'edinennykh Vlasovtsev (KOV), 1950-1953 (Folder 3: 23)
  - Natsional'naia Organizatsiia Russkikh Skautov, circa 1920 (Folder 3: 24)
  - Obshchestvo Gallipoliĭtsev, 1933-1951 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Rossiĭskoe Natsional'noe Ob"edinenie (RNO), 1931-1952 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Rossiĭskoe Natsional'noe Ob"edinenie (RNO), (contd.), 1931-1952 (Folder 4: 1-2)
  - Russkiĭ Obshche-Voinskiĭ Soiuz (ROVS), 1930-1941 (Folder 4: 3-6)
  - Soiuz Mladorossov, 1932-1933 (Folder 4: 7)
- Printed matter, 1898-1978. (Box 4-5)
  Periodicals arranged in two groups by size, then alphabetically.
  - General, 1910-1979
    - Bulletin d'information de l'Union Nationale Russe en Belgique, No.6, 1973 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Dobroe Staroe Vremia, belletristicheskiĭ periodicheskiĭ sbornik, Nice, 1931 (Folder 4: 9)
    - Livre blanc, Brussels, 1967-1970 (Folder 4: 10)
    - Nasha Pravda, Organe des Démocrates Soviétiques, No. 87, 1968; No. 99, 1970; No 103, 1977; No. 103, 1971; No. 112, 1972 (Folder 4: 11)
    - Posev, No. 6, 1979 (Folder 4: 12)
    - Rubezh, No.21 (382), Harbin, 1935 (Folder 4: 13)
    - Russkaia Rech', No. 81, 1910 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Russkiĭ Ochag, Paris, No. 1, 1934 (Folder 4: 15)
    - Russkiĭ Trud, Moscow, No. 36, 1909 (Folder 4: 16)
    - Suvorov, Vestnik Ob"edineniia Ofitserov General'nago Shtaba, San Francisco, No. 2, 1932 (Folder 4: 17)
    - Vestnik, Brussels, No. 6, 1934 (Folder 4: 18)
    - Vestnik Zdorov'ia, Saint Petersburg, 1911 (Folder 4: 19)
    - Vzlëty, Lyon, No. 2, 1933 (Folder 4: 20)
  - Oversize material, 1898-1979
    - Clippings, 1902-1929 (Folder 5: 1)
    - Edinyĭ Front Novoĭ Rossii, Paris, No. 20, 1936 (Folder 5: 2)
    - L'Illustration, Paris, clippings, 1905-1907 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Iskry, illustrirovannyĭ khudozhestvenno-literaturnyĭ i iumoristicheskiĭ zhurnal" s" karikaturami, Moscow, clippings, 1909-1914 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Iuzhnyi Krai, Khar'kov, illiustrirovannoe pribavlenie k No. 10235, 1911 (Folder 5: 5)
    - J'ai vu.., illustré paraissant tous les jeudis, Paris, No. 1, 1914 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Kievskaia Gazeta, Kiev, No. 16, 1905 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Le Monde colonial illustré, Paris, No. 88, 1930 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Nedelia, informatsionnyĭ organ russkoĭ kolonii v Bel'gii, Brussels, Nos. 1-2, 1934 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Nouvelles soviétiques, bulletin du bureau d'information de l'ambassade de l'U.R.S.S., Paris, No. 55, 1945 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Rossiia, New York, Vol. XVIII, No. 4489, 1950 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Russkaia Nedelia, informatsionnyĭ organ russkoĭ kolonii v" Bel'gii, Brussels, No. 2, 1934 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Russkaia Rech, Odessa, pribavlenie k" Nos. 702 and 912, 1908 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Russie-URSS, journal mensuel, Paris, No. 1, 1947 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Russkiia Vedomosti, Moscow, No. 251, 1898 (Folder 5: 9)
    - Russkiĭ Invalid, Paris, No. 170, 1977 and No. 172, 1979 (Folder 5: 10)
    - Russkiĭ v Anglii, London, No. 8/80, 1939 (Folder 5: 11)
    - Sotrudnik, collaborateur commercial Russe, Paris, No. 1, 1925 (Folder 5: 11)
    - Staryi Narvskiĭ Listok, Narva, No. 147(1065), 1932 (Folder 5: 11)
    - Tsarskiĭ Vestnik, Belgrad, Nos. 263, 1932; 398, 1934; 461, 1935 (Folder 5: 12)
    - Veche, Moscow, Nos. 73 and 78, 1907 (Folder 5: 13)
- Photographs, undated (Folder 5: 14)
  - "Gosudar' prinimaet parad Kavaleriĭskago polka" (Folder 5: 14)
  - "10. Voenno-Gruzinskaia doroga. Dvorets" i tserkov" kniazeĭ Kazbekskikh" (Folder 5: 14)
  - "14. Voenno-Gruzinskaia doroga. Kobiĭskiĭ spusk" (Folder 5: 14)
- Maps, 1890-1901 (Folder 5: 15)
  - "Plan" goroda Odessy, izadanie K. Viskovskago, dozvoleno tsenzuroiu 30 Aprelia 1890 goda," (Plan of Odessa), circa 1890 (Folder 5: 15)
  - "Plan" Khar'kova, glavnoe depo manufaktur "Novosteĭ" Fedora Grigor'evicha Enurovskago (starshago) v" Khar'kovi"," (Plan of Kharkov), 1901 (Folder 5: 15)